A Guide to the Cleveland Family Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #1999
Cleveland Family Papers 1858-1943
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
1999
115 items
Lt. E. W. Gregory
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was placed on loan with the Library on September 28, 1944, by Lt. E. W. Gregory of Norfolk, Virginia, through Miss Nellie George.
Scope and Content
This collection of 115 items, 1858-1943, contains the papers of Eva Cleveland(1868-1944), a well-known music teacher and choir director in Charlottesville whose musical career spanned fifty-eight years, 1886 to 1944, and a ledger from the A. H. Cleaveland Dry Goods Store. A. H. Cleaveland owned and managed the Cleaveland Dry Goods Store on Main Street in Charlottesville, Virginia, at least during the dates of his ledger, 1858-1875. His wife ran a small school, Cleaveland School, which began in 1876 and continued until at least the first decade of the twentieth century.
Ms. M. Eva Cleaveland(who later dropped both her first initial and the "a" in Cleaveland) and her sister Kate Cleaveland were accomplished musicians who were known locally for their talent in singing and playing the piano. A younger sister, Carrie Cleaveland, was later a student in Ms. Eva Cleveland's school. After completing school and musical training at New York University and the Cincinnati Conservatory of Music, Ms. Eva Cleveland taught music at her mother's school at least during the 1887-1888 session, but by 1892 she had her own music school which continued under her direction until 1943. "Miss Eva," as she was known locally, was also the organist and choir director of First Baptist Church of Charlottesville for twenty-five years. The many newspaper clippings kept by Ms. Eva Cleveland attest to her skills both in playing and teaching music, and generations of Charlottesville youth spent years under her tutelage.
The collection of Ms. Eva Cleveland's papers include miscellaneous memorabilia of the Charlottesville area, programs of music recitals, and a scrapbook filled with newspaper clippings of local interest and recipes. Of particular value to local historians are printed materials on the First Baptist Church of Charlottesville and various printed materials pertaining to Charlottesville and Albemarle County. There are "patriotic" pamphlets, and a program from the Medical College of Virginia's 1936 commencement exercises, numerous recital programs listing local youth, and newspaper clippings discussing local events, musical and other.
Container List
- TOPICAL
  - Music Recital Programs: Ms. Cleveland's School and the First Baptist Church, 1892-1943, n.d.
    [for whom Ms. Eva Cleveland served as choir director]
  - Music Recital Programs: Other Local Music Schools, 1892-1941, n.d.
  - Printed Materials: First Baptist Church of Charlottesville, Virginia, 1905-1941
    [Bulletin of Dedicatory Service, programs, and a 1941 church directory.]
  - Printed Materials: Charlottesville and Albemarle County, 1875-1940, n.d.
    [Includes prints of local buildings, program of 1922 Albemarle Homecoming Celebration, battlefield markers information, and a copy of the town charter.]
  - Miscellaneous: Booklets, 1876-1919, n.d.
    [on etiquette, recipes, historical figures and patriotic issues.]
  - Miscellaneous: Music, 1891-1928, n.d.
    [Includes a copy of an 1896 New York Musical Echo, information on composers, booklets on piano exercises and teaching.]
  - Miscellaneous, 1859-1938, n.d.
    [Items of personal interest to Ms. Eva Cleveland. Includes pages from an 1859 edition of the Georgia Temperance Crusader, brochures from her mother's school, poems, and souvenirs of vacation trips]
  - Ledger-Scrapbook, 1884-1930's, n.d.
    [Ledger, presumably of her father's, used as a scrapbook, which contains recipes, articles about beauty and household issues, and clippings about local social events and reviews of Ms. Eva Cleveland's church and school's recitals.]
- Ledger of A. H. Cleaveland Dry Goods Store, 1858-1875
  [listing accounts]